hey everyone welcome back to this task
automation playlist and today we are
going to continue with another Excel
feature which is available in Tosca
now we have already seen how you can
create this particular Excel workbook
with a new uh Excel worksheet and even
you can enter different values into your
Excel cells right so just like we have
prepared this employee worksheet okay
with some employee names and salaries
and total salary we have also verified
it using different Excel modules present
in the standard subset
now if you have not watched this video I
would recommend to go back to our
Channel and watch this video first and
then come back to this video where I'm
going to explain you how you can use the
same t-box modules to basically find the
row count and column count for your
Excel sheet okay so for this particular
Excel sheet you can see there are four
rows right and there are two columns so
that is what we want to verify or we
want to find out after we create some
Excel sheet or for an existing Excel
sheet okay
so let's go back to Tosca and here you
can see I have got already two test
cases one is to compare to Excel files
and one is to create uh an Excel sheet
with some values in it right now I'm
going to create a third test case and
I'm going to show you how you can get
the row count and column count of your
Excel sheet using the Excel modules
present in Tosca okay so I'm going to
name it get row count
and column count
okay and we are going to reuse some of
the test steps okay so these are
basically the tree box modules which we
have used earlier so I'll be using the
open Excel bug book I'll be using Define
excel range okay and a close Excel
workbook so these three modules I'll be
reusing here
we need to make some changes quickly
okay so I don't want to create any new
um Excel workbook I will be using the
same Excel workbook which is already
created so I will change it to false
and then Excel range okay so workbook
name worksheet name and the range name
will remain same
here close Excel workbook so that's also
fine right now I'm going to add one more
module here so let's go out to our test
step and here we will try and find Excel
range manipulation okay the last one
and uh we are going to drag it before
the close Excel workbook here I'm going
to change this name and name it to get
row count
okay and then I'm going to copy this and
paste it again okay and again I'm going
to place it here and I'm going to change
this to get column count
okay so these are the two test steps
built from the same module which is the
Excel range manipulation right
so in this we have got the range name so
we'll keep it so that it can find that
particular range okay which we have
defined already
and we're going to paste it here in the
data table we just need to uh get the
row count okay and how you can do that
so under the value just click on this
Arrow okay and here you will see you can
Define some property and some value
right so here I'm going to uh make it
row count okay and here I'm going to
give some value called RC or variable
name okay and I'm going to change this
action mode to buffer
so what it is going to do is it is going
to get the row count okay so it's a
special property which can get the row
count from a table in Tosca and then it
will assign that value to RC okay
similar thing you need to do it here
you can also directly type this okay
but let's do it this way so again column
count
and then uh in the value we'll put it CC
okay and then we'll change this to
buffer
right so
RC and CC are the buffer values so that
will contain the actual row count and
column count of this particular table
right
so that's all you need to do uh to get
the row count in column count for your
Excel workbook right let's go ahead and
run this now
okay so this is going to fail because my
file is already open right so whenever
you run uh any anything with an Excel
sheet or Excel workbook you need to make
sure that the Excel is not in use okay
so let's go ahead and close our Excel
okay save it
so let's try and run it again but before
that I just noticed that we missed one
thing okay so in the get column count
test tip we did not give the range name
so let's give this employee data
and just just verify okay so both the
range names are present and let's try
and run this again hopefully this time
it will pass
okay so the test case has passed and if
I look at the results right if we go
into the log info you can see uh range
employee data is updated successfully
and then in the row count
you will see that the RC has been set to
Value 4 okay so that's our buffer and
then the column count uh
okay it has been set to two so we had
four rows and we had two columns and
that's what it is storing in the buffer
now if you want to verify a certain row
count and column count you can just use
this buffer values and put a
verification step later on okay so that
we already know so I'm not going to do
it I will leave it for you to do it
okay so that's how easy it is to find
the row and column count of a particular
Excel workbook it may be an existing one
or if you are creating a new one you can
still add the steps and then you can
verify the row count and column count
so that's all for this video I hope you
enjoyed it and you learned something new
today
if you have got any questions just leave
it in the comments and do share it with
others who might find it useful also
don't forget to subscribe to our channel
so that you don't miss out on any new
videos being uploaded to our Channel
until the next video keep watching and
keep learning